第7集：猎手与猎物
猎手与猎物之间的斗争最能展现生存竞争的激烈
Life is at its most intense during the struggles between predator and prey.
每一方想存活
Each side, to survive,
就必须比对方聪明，懂得生存的策略
must outwit and outmanoeuvre the other.
作为奖励，猎手得到的是一顿美食
The prize, for the hunter...a meal.
对于猎物而言，就是能多活一天的机会
For the prey,the chance to live another day.
《 猎 手 和 猎 物 》
三只雄性的花豹
Three male cheetahs.
这三兄弟比较特别
These brothers are very special.
他们敢于猎杀一些其他猎手不敢碰的猎物
They hunt prey few other cheetahs would dare to tackle.
要想成功，首先得选择捕猎对象
To succeed,they must first select a victim.
并一起围捕它
And then work together to overpower it.
这是个危险的活
It's dangerous work.
成年的斑马蹄，是可以致命的
An adult zebra is potentially lethal.
结果是不能预测的
The outcome is by no means certain.
第一只豹被赶走了
The first cheetah is driven off.
他的兄弟，也犯了一直致命的错误
And his brothers have already made a critical mistake.
他们没能靠近猎物，到足够的距离
They aren't close enough to take over the attack.
又追向不同的猎物
Each is chasing a different target,
这样便于成年斑马保护小斑马
making it easy for the zebra to defend their young.
250公斤的斑马，终于给他们机会了
A quarter-tonne stallion finally puts paid to their chances.
追逐不同的目标，注定是不会成功的
Chasing different zebra was bound to lead to failure.
或者他们的热情比较高涨
Perhaps their enthusiasm got the better of them.
他们必须继续尝试
They must try again.
在肯亚山的阴影下，兄弟们重新相聚
In the shadow of Mount Kenya,the brothers regroup.
他们对斑马的错误策略
Their mistake with the zebra was to hunt as ordinary cheetahs do -
和其他豹一样，就是单独追猎目标
as individuals.
对付这样的猎物，他们必须另想办法
To catch such prey, they must hunt like no other cheetahs.
一起行动
That means acting together,
as one.
他们重新开始了
They start again.
一只鸵鸟，比任何花豹都要重
An ostrich outweighs and outguns a single cheetah.
这次他们只有一个目标
This time there's only one target.
三兄弟一起行动
And all three cheetahs are onto it.
老三，开始袭击鸵鸟
The third brother starts to throttle the ostrich.
就算能避开鸵鸟的腿
它依然是一只危险的猎物
Even off its feet,it's still dangerous.
兄弟们找到了独有的捕猎方法
The brothers have found a unique way of catching their prey.
有能力发明这种聪明的捕猎方法
The ability to invent such novel hunting tactics
是哺乳类动物，优胜于其他动物
is one thing that really sets mammals apart.
但是哺乳类动物
也可能随时成为别人的猎物
But mammals themselves can also be targets for predators,
而每一次捕猎，需要采取不同的策略
and the hunted also need to devise special tactics.
死海沙漠的边缘
The desert shores of the Dead Sea.
在这里生存，真的是非常困难
Living here is difficult indeed.
现在是三月
It's March, and high on these cathedral cliffs,
在这些高耸的峭壁上
阿尔卑斯 野山羊，在这里生育
ibex have given birth.
最初的日子，小山羊是安全的
For the first few days the kids were kept safe,
有这些悬崖隔离
isolated on the cliff tops.
但是现在他们要面对难题了
But now the ibex have a problem.
食物和水源，都远在峡谷的最下面
The only food and water is far below at the bottom of the gorge.
这正是猎食者，潜伏的地方
And that is where predators lurk.
他们一定要冒险，才能觅食
If they're to feed,it's a risk they will have to take.
成年的山羊领路
The adults lead the way.
他们知道最安全的路线
They know the safest routes.
当然这里的安全，只是相对的
Though safe, here,is a relative term.
小山羊，只能紧跟在后
The kids have no choice but to keep up.
一失足，就可能丧命
One slip could be the last.
属于偶蹄目的他们
有在这里行走的天赋
Their only assets are cloven hooves that spread under load,
他们有惊人的平衡能力
astonishing balance...
加上非常敏捷
..and the most uncanny agility.
出生才七天，就天性无畏
Barely a week old,they are utterly fearless.
学会在悬崖行走
是他们生存的重点
Learning to negotiate these cliffs is central to their survival.
现在这家人
必须警惕掠食者了
But now the family must be on guard against predators.
提高每一分警觉
All grab a chance to browse.
最后一头小羊也来了
Trailing behind,the last youngster is almost down.
正好遇到麻烦
And runs right into trouble.
一只狐狸
A fox.
这个流浪者在等待
It's been waiting for the straggler.
小山羊从没见过狐狸，但天性告诉它，这是一个危险
The kid has never seen a fox before,
but knows it's in real peril.
在跑回山上的时候，他遇到更大的麻烦――悬崖
It appears to be running into more trouble,as it heads back up the cliff.
狐狸企图爬上去
The fox tries to gain the higher ground.
但是小山羊找到一个非常陡峭的悬崖
But the kid has found safety
只有阿尔卑斯山羊才能站立在这里
on a face so steep that only an ibex could stand there.
早上下山的时候所学到的一切，救了他一命
The lessons learnt on this morning's descent
have saved its life.
狐狸只能放弃这艰难的捕猎
Finally, the fox gives it up as a bad job...
或者他突然发现自己站在危险的灾难边缘
..perhaps suddenly aware it's standing on a precipice.
就算小小年纪，在这里小山羊的生存智慧还是胜过
Despite its tender age,
the ibex has outwitted one of the canniest of predators.
最狡猾的猎食者
狐狸这次失败，显示了猎食者的困境
The fox's failure epitomises a predator's plight.
捕猎并不是容易的
Most hunts fail,so hunters are continually devising new tactics.
所以猎食者要经常尝试新的技巧
在巴西的热带雨林
The rainforests of Belize in Central America.
当夜幕低垂，大雨将至
And as evening falls and the shower comes to an end,
一位猎手开始行动
a predator begins to hunt.
巨大的“都牛犬”蝙蝠
The greater bulldog bat.
唯一会飞行哺乳类动物
A flying mammal...
它是一位“渔翁”
..and a fisherman.
一条正好游近水面的鱼引起的涟漪
A fish swimming just below the surface creates tell-tale ripples
这恰是蝙蝠，需要的信息
and that is all the bat needs to detect them.
只要一个微弱的抖动
With little more than a fin to aim for,
这位猎手，以40哩的时速
and whilst flying at 40 miles an hour,
扑向鱼的位置
the bat takes the fish completely unawares.
只要浅水有任何震动
If the shoal scatters...
掠过水面的蝙蝠
..the bat trawls the surface.
就会像拖网船一样，大肆捕捞
Raking the water,trying to snag a fish.
但有利的捕鱼位置不会很久
He won't have the best fishing spot to himself for long,
其他蝙蝠，很快抵达
and soon, other bats arrive.
繁忙的交通使捕鱼变得几乎“不可能”
Oncoming traffic would make grabbing a fish almost impossible,
他们开始鸣叫，避免碰撞
so the bats avoid collisions by honking -
他们争相发出“在这，别撞过来！”
dropping their calls an octave to say, "Look out, here I come!"
很快，这片浅滩就水泄不通
Soon the shoal has either been captured or has fled,
蝙蝠在继续捕捞着…
and the bats move on.
这种技巧，是需要实践去锻炼的
Skills like this take practice,
有些哺乳类，从小就开始实践锻炼
and for some mammals that practice begins in infancy.
一只小鼬鼠
A young stoat.
他不是单独的
And it's not alone.
STOATS CHIRP
这种野外游戏很吸引它
These wild game sare too much to resist.
在游戏中，可以练习埋伏、突击、追逐
Stalking, chasing and ambushing,all practised in play.
很快,小鼬鼠必须自己觅食
Soon the young stoats must hunt for themselves,
而这些技巧是必须的
and then these athletic skills will be crucial.
这是九月英国的田野
It's September in the English countryside.
这只小鼬鼠准备对付一个体积十倍的敌人
This stoat is about to take on
an adversary ten times its size.
但直接攻击，是非常危险的
It's too dangerous to rush straight in.
然而，小鼬鼠的目的，是消耗兔子体力
Instead, the stoat's aim is to wear the rabbit down.
兔子的力量在衰退，而小鼬鼠的耐力开始使局面发生了变化。
The rabbit is flagging,and the stoat's stamina is starting to make a difference.
但是单有耐力还不够，必须有将兔子击倒的攻击才行
But stamina alone is not enough -the rabbit must still be overpowered.
SQUEALING
对兔子的颈后的一咬，成为了致命的攻击
A bite to the back of the neck and a kill.
这惊人的准确性，是它在玩耍时就已经学会的技巧
The incredible agility of the stoat,practised since it was a kit,
这对于它来说，是运用自如
was just enoughb to swing the balance.
有时候，光靠体力是不能战胜对手的
There are times when mere physical powers
捕猎者要成功，必须有优势
are not enough to give the hunter an edge.
哺乳类发展了他们的专业――脑袋
Then mammals must deploy their most sophisticated weapon - their brains.
在福罗里达州的海床上，有些奇怪的图案
Strange patterns are visible in the mud of Florida Bay,
我们可以看到，一种特别的捕猎方法
a faint hint of a unique hunting tactic.
罪犯是
The perpetrators...
瓶鼻海豚
..bottlenose dolphins.
他们正在准备捕鱼
And they're on a mission -a mission to catch fish.
这里的鱼是非常难捕获的
The fish here are very difficult to catch
在这种浅水区，他们应当很安全
and in such shallow water they ought to be safe.
但是海豚们有他们的计划
Yet the dolphins have a plan.
他们懂得如何分工合作、围捕这种鱼
They have learnt to corral the fish by working as a team.
为首的海豚，用尾巴拍打海床
The lead dolphin beats its tail on the sea bed,
卷起环状的泥土
stirring up a ring of mud.
鱼很自然不敢，穿越浑浊的海水
Trapped inside, the fish take their only way out,
他们企图跳出这个
“煎锅”却掉进了“火炉”
but they're leaping out of the frying pan and into the fire.
一旦短暂的泥圈消失，鱼就大肆逃窜
Once the mud ring loses its shape,the fish scatter.
所以海豚要不断重复这个过程
The dolphins move on and repeat the process.
运用大脑和团队合作，是制胜的法宝
Brain power combined with team work -it's a winning formula.
这是福罗里达州海豚，独有的捕猎方法
This behaviour is unique to the dolphins of Florida Bay.
子女从父母处学习
Successive generations have learnt it from their parents
然后再由他们传授给后代
and in turn they will teach it to their own young.
这种传授复杂技能的行为
The ability to pass on such complex behaviours
是哺乳类动物的天赋
is one of the mammals'greatest talents.
这是他们赖以生存的技能
It enables them to survive where others would perish.
寒冬正接近阿拉斯加
As winter approaches in Alaska,
食物越来越难找
food gets progressively harder to find.
在这里生活是非常艰苦的
To live here is to walk a tightrope.
但是每一年，这片海岸却引来北美洲最厉害的猎手
Yet every year, this coast attracts North America's most impressive hunter.
棕熊
A brown bear.
在这里他们比生长在世界任何地方的同类都大
Here they grow larger than anywhere in the world.
他们聚集等待
Other bears have also gathered at the edge of the surf.
他们是来增肥过冬的
They've come here to fatten up for the winter.
他们正等待一年一度的盛宴
They're waiting for an event that happens just once a year.
三文鱼大餐
The salmon run.
很多熊，选择河流上游，狭窄处等候
Others will tackle the fish upriver, but here in the sea,
但是，这些熊却捷足先登
these bears have the first chance.
冬天，熊的生存，都是靠这些鱼来维持
Each bear's survival depends on this run of fish staying strong.
有些年头他们的等待会白费，因为鱼没有出现
There are years when their gamble
fails and the fish hardly show.
熊只能面对饥饿
Then the bears face starvation.
今年他们得到了，丰盛的大餐
This year promises to be a bumper one
他们体重大增，以备寒冬
and the bears will be able to pile on the pounds ahead of winter.
哺乳类动物很懂得利用这种团体的力量
Mammals are supreme in their ability to
exploit such fleeting opportunities.
盛宴终止，冬天降临
Chances come and go with the passing of the seasons.
但对于某些捕猎者而言，每一年都是非常艰苦的
But for some predators, conditions
are tough whatever the time of year.
看上去，这些山岭似乎是渺无生命
At first glance, these mountains seem barren and empty of life.
像是漂浮于云中的岛屿
Like islands thrust up into the sky,
他们突出在附近的高原
they tower above the surrounding plains.
其实他们是避难所
Yet, far from being deserted,they are a refuge.
在这被隔离的非洲屋脊
Isolated here,on the roof of Africa,
有世界上罕见的猎手
is one of the rarest hunters in the world.
埃塞俄比亚狼
The Ethiopian wolf.
非洲唯一的狼
The only wolf in the whole of Africa.
就算处于赤道，这些山峰的晚上还是很冷的
Despite being close to the equator,these peaks are so cold at night
狼，面对着霜冻的清晨
that the wolves face a frost-covered dawn.
每一群狼都由一位成年的女皇带领
Each pack is centred around a single dominant female.
通常只有一头母狼负责生育
Normally it is only she who breeds.
这一年，她生了六只小狼
This year she has produced six pups.
但是如果她要在这荒芜之地，让他们全部存活
But if she is to raise them all in this barren land,
她就需要整群狼的帮助
she will need the help of the entire pack.
每个早上，狼群出发捕猎
Every morning,the pack sets off to hunt,
只留下她，在石堆中照顾小狼
leaving her back among the rocks with the pups.
他们在山上，大概5平方英里内捕猎
The pack's hunting ground is about five square miles of mountain top.
他们把狩猎场围个水泄不通
They guard it zealously,
每天巡逻边界
patrolling its frontiers every day.
他们密切合作
Wolves elsewhere co-operate
是企图猎杀大猎物？
and use their united power to pull down big prey.
但是这里没有巨大的唇鹿
But there are no caribou or moose to be found up here.
他们分开
The pack splits up.
首先单独狩猎
Each member is going to hunt alone.
其中一位发现了什么？
One of them spots something.
小老鼠
It's a rat.
无论你如何隐蔽捕捉老鼠，不是件容易的事
But catching rats is not easy, no
matter how carefully you stalk them.
他们发明了更主动的方法
Another hunter has a more pro-active technique.
成功了！
RAT SCREECHES And that works.
花这么大力气，换来小小的收获
It's a lot of work for relatively small rewards,
还要这种独特的狩猎技巧
and demands its own particular style of hunting.
一位猎手回来了
A hunter returns.
猎手捐出了，母狼索要的食物
Mother demands food and the successful hunter delivers it.
尽管是这么小的一份
So rearing a single litter here
但，这是集体的力量
takes the combined labour of a dozen or so adults
这就是狼，得以生存的策略调整
and the Ethiopian wolves have adjusted their behaviour accordingly.
适应环境，也是哺乳类动物的强项
That adaptability is the mammals' great strength,
这令他们在这种好像不能生存的环境中存活下来
enabling them to survive in some very unlikely habitats.
一只星鼻鼹鼠
A star-nosed mole,
他具有可能是这地球上最独特的鼻子
possessor of perhaps the most
extraordinary nose on the planet.
他的鼻孔，有22只手指状的组织
Its nostrils are surrounded by twenty-two fingers.
这让他仅凭这些手指与外界的接触，就足以获得外界的信息
Fingers that allow the mole to sense the world around it by touch alone.
通过接触他就可以用惊人的速度找到猎物
It enables it to detect food with astonishing speed.
他会游泳
It can also swim...
在水中，他不平凡的鼻子也能帮助他
..and once underwater, its nose helps it in a most extraordinary way.
它吹出一个气泡又吸回
It blows out a bubble and breathes it back in,
能用1/1000秒来侦测附近的猎物
detecting in a millisecond if there's prey close by.
这种方法能让他在水中寻找食物
This bubble-blowing allows it to sniff out its food underwater,
但这很快使他的氧气储备用完
but, unfortunately, that means it soon runs out of breath.
所以他要很敏捷地去捕猎
So it's just as well that it can hunt as fast down here as on the surface.
很少动物能如此迅速地捕猎
Few creatures can hunt equally successfully underground and underwater.
无论在地面或水下
印度，宾达威格 国家公园
Bandhavgarh, India,
在最干旱的季节
at the height of the dry season.
一只印度梅花鹿
A chital deer.
他必须分分秒秒都保持警惕
They must live their lives with all their senses at a high pitch.
最微弱的气味
The faintest smell,
再细小的声音
the slightest sound,
最迅速的一瞥
the briefest glimpse
观察是否有危险
could give warning of an attack.
梅花鹿发必须发现它们的敌人
The chital must detect their enemy
在它们突袭自己以前
before it takes them by surprise.
他们有盟友
And they have allies.
灵猴
Langur monkeys.
好的眼力和有利的地形
Keen eyesight and a perch high in the trees
他们能观察到整个森林
means they can scan the forest.
森林会充满，各种分心的事情
The jungle is full of distraction.
高度紧张地，防止危险的发生
Senses are strained,trying to detect approaching danger.
一群梅花鹿
Yet the chital still need to feed.
猎手，要缩短伏击的距离
And the hunter must get within striking distance.
在风中有一丝危险的提示
There's a hint of danger carried on the wind.
他们分外紧张
The herd shares a nervousness.
DEER CALLS
其实不应该跑，你并没有看见猎手
You should never run from what you can't see,
这样只会令你，走向另一个危险
you might just run straight into danger.
老虎已经靠的够近了
The tiger is nearly close enough to launch her attack.
但是她必须等待
She must wait.
再靠近一点
The chital need to come just a little closer.
但是她再靠近，就会被灵猴发现
If she moves now,the langurs will see her.
MONKEY BARKS, DEER CALLS
梅花鹿发现并跑掉了
The deer had a moment's head start,and escape.
警觉的灵猴，救了梅花鹿
The langurs' vigilance saved the chital.
老虎只能挨饿了
And the tiger goes hungry.
对于有些哺乳动物来说，攻击是最好的防御
For some mammals,attack is the best form of defence.
松鼠在武装自己
This squirrel is arming herself.
这只加利福尼亚，地松鼠发现了蛇皮
It's a California ground squirrel,and she's found a snake skin.
她把它嚼烂，并擦涂在身上
She's chewing it into a paste
尤其是她的尾巴
which she then rubs into her fur,especially her tail.
现在，她身上有一般蛇的气味
She now stinks of snake.
她生存的地方，包括草原和牧场
She lives in a colony that extends across a wide expanse of prairie.
另外，在她生活地方
There is one downside to this neighbourhood -
也是响尾蛇，居住的地方
it's in the middle of rattlesnake country.
尤其当你要抚育后代时
Not good when you have young to raise.
SQUIRREL CHIRPS
她的邻居好像感觉到什么
Her neighbour has sensed something.
一条响尾蛇，就住在他们洞穴的附近
A rattlesnake,hidden right next to their burrow.
他们会如何做呢？
They both investigate but what can they do?
这会激怒响尾蛇
Kicking stones only provokes the snake.
RATTLING
在千钧一发的时刻
Rattlesnakes sense prey by the heat they give off
松鼠会利用
and the squirrel is able to take advantage of this.
他，竖起的蓬松尾巴
She heats up her tail with warm blood.
不断摆动，来恐吓响尾蛇
Waving it at the snake is a threat.
这使她看上去，体型更大
It makes her look much larger than she is.
SNAKE RATTLES
而且她尾巴上的气味，更像是蛇
And the scent of rattler on her fluffed tail
她竟然在模仿响尾蛇
intimidates the snake.
蛇决定撤退
It decides to retreat.
然而，松鼠感到住在这里太危险了
The mother decides this part of
the neighbourhood is too dangerous,
她搬家了
and moves her young to new quarters.
如果幸运，新的居所，可能是理想的
With luck, this may be a safer place to raise a family.
猎手和猎物，都必须不断地精研他们的策略
Both predator and prey must endlessly refine their strategies.
偶而, 一些动物会有突破性的策略
Just occasionally, an individual makes a unique breakthrough
掌握了一些崭新的技巧
and learns to do something completely new.
12月，寒风凛冽的福克兰群岛
It's December, and a storm rages around the Falkland Islands.
巴布亚企鹅，面对暴风雪和沙石
Gentoo penguins face blizzards of blown sand.
小海象，在危险的岩石边
Young elephant seals risk being dragged off the rocks by the surging waves
被汹涌的海浪冲入海里
and swept out into open water.
虎鲸，一种大型的海洋动物
Orca - the largest and most predatory of the dolphin family.
我们熟悉的杀人鲸
Killer whales.
这群虎鲸，共有九条。要在这里生存，必需抓紧机会
This pod of nine can only survive here by being opportunists.
一般来说，小海象并不是菜单上的猎物
Normally, young elephant seals are not on the menu.
他们一般远离大海
They stay close to the shore,safe in the shallows of their nursery pool.
在他们的抚育场所
The pool is almost entirely cut off from the sea.
由一处窄长的浅水地带连接
A narrow, shallow channel is the only access to the open water.
但是这群杀人鲸里，有一条特别的雌性
But this pod of killer whales contains a very special female.
她带着幼鲸
She's easily identified by her calf,which is always close by.
每年她都会来这里
Every year she comes to the pool at the same time,
当海狮游进浅海
when the seals first swim in the shallows.
她就懂得如何去捕获他们
She knows how to get them.
穿过狭窄的水道，是她的第一个挑战
Negotiating the channel is her first challenge.
在小水滩开口处的水，刚好比较深
The water near the mouth of the pool is slightly deeper.
她就在这里伏击
Here she sets her ambush,
等待海狮游到深水处
waiting for a seal to stray out of the shallows.
对于这位母亲和她的幼子来说这是危险的
For mother and calf,this is an extremely risky ploy.
她必须不断地衡量海浪的大小
She must continuously assess how big
the waves are, how deep the water is
水的深浅、和潮汐的涨落
and what the tide is doing.
稍有不慎，她们将会搁浅
One bad decision would see both mother and calf stranded.
海狮在浅水处，还离她们很远
The seals lie in the shallows,
也没察觉，他们的到来
just out of reach and unaware of her presence.
不过她不单只在衡量海浪的变化
But she is more than aware of the dropping tide.
惊慌失措的海狮，引起了他们的注意
A floundering seal catches her attention...
因为带着幼鲸，他比较谨慎地靠近浅水区
..and with her calf,she slowly moves towards it.
海狮正好躺在岩石的突出处
The seal is lying right on the edge of a rocky ledge,
危险得很
oblivious to the danger.
这伸延突出的岩石，使杀人鲸无法靠近
The projecting ledge keeps the seal just out of reach.
但是她已经有个计划
Yet she has a plan.
前后移动，她制造波浪
Rocking back and forth,she's making a wave,
以便把海狮，冲出这块岩石
trying to wash the seal off the ledge.
但是海草的存在，增加了难度
But it is securely surrounded by kelp.
一个浪花提醒了她，她有更好的主意
A splash alerts her to a better opportunity.
另一只海狮开始游进这个小水滩
Another seal has started to swim into the pool.
她的机会来了
This is her chance.
她冒着危险，游到浅水区
Edging further into the shallows than ever before,she's risking everything.
冲上沙滩，将海狮咬到嘴里
Half beached and with a struggling seal in her mouth,
再用尽全力把他拖下水
it takes all her strength to drag it out of the pool.
她是在这地球上唯一懂得这样
She is the only killer whale on the planet
捕杀海狮的杀人鲸
that knows how to hunt these seals in this way
重要的是，她现在正传授给幼鲸这个技巧
and, crucially, she's now passing on that skill to her own calf.
这样巧妙的策略
Extraordinary strategies like these
驱使着每一个猎手和猎物
lie at the heart of the struggle between predator and prey.
他们要生存，就得适应大自然的无情
They're born of a conflict that is relentless and unforgiving.
命运把猎手和猎物，紧紧地联系起来
A conflict that eternally binds the hunter and the hunted.
将来看似充满希望
It's looking very promising.
BBC Life 团队订立了一个艰难的目标给自己
The Life team had set themselves a tough challenge
在拍摄这些非常的捕猎场面
in trying to film exceptional hunting sequences,
但是他们很幸运
but our teams were lucky enough
他们有机会观察到世界上最有趣的捕猎者
to observe some of the world's most charismatic predators.
看看这些福克兰群岛的虎鲸
It was the killer whales of the Falklands, though,
带领着摄制队，到达了最近的拍摄地点
that brought the team closest to the action.
每一年在这海狮岛上
Every year, off Sea Lion Island,
杀人鲸都会把幼小的海狮拖下海
killer whales snatch young elephant seals from their nursery pool.
拍摄这些镜头
Filming most hunting sequences involves
通常需要相当的耐心和一点幸运
a great deal of waiting and a slice of luck,
但是在这里事情有点不同
but here things were a little different.
摄影师和制作人，远渡福克兰群岛
Cameraman Mike Pitts and producer Adam Chapman travelled to the Falklands
他们听说这里，每年当中有二个月
having heard that, for two weeks each year,
杀人鲸会到来
killer whales focuson one particular spot.
杀人鲸懂得寻找年幼的海象作为目标
The killer whales have learnt to target elephant seal pups
而且是当他们第一次下水时
as they first venture into the water
这样摄制组就有充分的时间去拍摄
and this gives the team their best chance of filming a hunt.
摄制队第一时间不但要熟悉这个拍摄场地
The first task facing the team is to familiarise
themselves not only with a new location
还要熟悉这些被拍摄的对象
but also with the animals they will be working around.
摄制组很快发觉，他们和拍摄仪器
And the team soon realise that they and their equipment
对小海象来说显得很新奇
are a great novelty to the seal pups.
我宁愿在镜头看他们
I daren't look into the camera
因为我担心，脚架被他们撞倒
because I'm more worried about the tripod being knocked over.
看，我们的小朋友来了
We've got a little friend here
我要投诉他们妨碍拍摄
so I'm gonna report him for interfering with the film crew.
小海象的好奇心令我们意外
The pups' fascination with the team is rather unexpected.
SEAL SNORTS
麦克，你对野生动物真有办法
You've got a great way with wildlife, Michael!
适应环境咯
At one with nature!
啊... 这里有点麻烦，就是他们实在太多了
It's quite difficult out here.There's so many of them.
大量的幼海象
The large number of youngsters bodes
对于杀人鲸来说是好事
well for the killer whales,
我们与小海象，相处越久
but the longerthe team spend with the pups,
我们就越喜欢他们
the more they warm to them.
当你看着这些小海象
When you look at these little pups
你一定会被他们吸引
you can't fail to be captivated by them,
尤其是当你注视他们的眼睛时
especially when you gaze into those eyes,
他们真的能牵动你的心
it really pulls on your heartstrings,
但是对于杀人鲸
but for an orca, of course,
他们只是20公斤的蛋白质
it's 120 kilos of pure protein,
所以杀人鲸在这里猎食
so that's why they're hunted.
日子越久
As the days go by,
摄制组对这里的感情就越深
the team continue to get a feel for the location,
突然间，杀人鲸抵达了
when suddenly
the killer whales arrive.
显然他们对这里，非常感兴趣
The pod of nine is clearly interested in the pool,
一条雌性杀人鲸，特别的自信
and one female is particularly confident.
她来了
She's coming in.
她和她的幼鲸，经常来这里
The female and her calf start to come into the pool regularly,
但是她们碰不到，远处的猎物
but there never seems to be a pup within reach.
我们来福克兰是准备在水底拍摄的
The team have come to the Falklands prepared to film underwater.
现在应该重新考虑一下，这个决定是否现实
Now the time has come to see if this is a realistic ambition.
SEAL EXHALES
杀人鲸在远方出现
With lookouts posted and the whales far away
摄影师就算能靠近
Mike is able to get in.
就算这样
Even so,
谁能责怪它那么紧张呢？
who can blame him for being jumpy?
Ah!          Whoo!
小海狮贪玩，对我们造成了困难
The pups' playfulness is becoming an issue -
最后有件事摄制队希望
the last thing the team want is
他们的拍摄，不会对这里的生态造成影响
to have any influence on the events they're here to film.
这也取决杀人鲸的反应
There's also the question of how the killer whales might react
对于在水里面的人来说
to a person in the water.
这里非常的合适
It's quite intimidating in there.
这里有个突出的地方
It shelves up, so I'm in the centre of the channel and it goes down to,
我拿不准，估计这里有8丈
I don't know, maybe eight feet I think
大概有个几米
a couple of metres.
但海水的能见度非常差
But the visibility's really stirred up.
他们怎么找到这条通道，真的不太清楚
How they find their way in that channel I just don't know.
我非常担心
如果我同事和杀人鲸进入这水道
And what I'm worried about is if I do get in the water with the orca...
因为要在水里，等上一段时间
Which I'm slightly concerned about,I have to say...
杀人鲸是来觅食的，而不是来度假
She's in a hunting mode,she's not here just for her to pass the time of day.
她是来杀戮的
She's out there to kill something,
大家都知道，我担心自己成为猎物
and, you know, I just don't want to be that person, or seal...
无论她怎样看待我
Whatever she thinks I am.
有可能咬我一口，才发现咬错了对象
She'll probably realise once she's bitten me that she's made a mistake
我不知道，这是否值得我赌上性命
and, I don't know,is it worth the gamble?
一周快要过去了,
With a week already gone,
杀人鲸还是没有再游回来
the killer whales have not
yet made a full-blown attack,
天气起了变化
and then the weather changes.
或许它会到别的地方,但我认为
Well, hopefully it'll blow itself out but I think ...
这个地方，会平静一段时间
The pool, it's going to be a couple of days before that calms down.
这风暴持续了二天
The storm rages for two more days,
十一天后，恢复了好天气
but on the eleventh day the good weather returns.
时间紧迫
Mike knows that time is running out.
而杀人鲸还是，离这里很远
Well, the orcas are out there,they're still quite a way off.
摄制组，决定放一台摄影机到杆上
The team decides a camera on the end of a pole
希望这能帮助拍摄水底的情况
might be the way to reveal the underwater action.
暴风过后，海底依然浑浊
After that storm,it's been so stirred up.
我们要将它稍微贴近水面
And just... Just bring it slightly out of the water, Adam,
拉……好……停！
so draw it back towards you and stop.
基本上很黑，漆黑一片
And it's dark, dark, green,basically, very dark green.
仍有许多...悬浮物，是的没错
There's still a lot of...Suspension, yeah.
风暴把海水搞的很浑浊
The storm had stirred up the pool
使我们很难看见任何东西
但我们还是保持很高的热情
making it hard to see anything,
but the team remain in good spirits.
穿这个我的屁股是不是显得很大?
确实很强大!
Does my bum look big in this?
Massive!
当小海狮准备第一次下海时
As the seal pups are nearly ready to go to sea,
杀人鲸，捕猎的时间，已经变得很少了
the whales' opportunity to hunt this year will soon pass
摄制组知道，这可能是最后的机会
and the team know this could be their last chance.
看看鳍的尺寸
Look at the size of that fin!
好了，麦克, 她来了
OK, Mike, she's coming in.
She's coming in, Mike.
来了？这里吗？
She's coming in? Just here.
麦克？
Mike?
等等
One second, mate.
这里可以了，我可以和你对话了
I can talk to you gently here now
我看见你指的了
and I can also see where you're pointing.
她来了
She's in.
我正在录，慢慢，稳定！
I'm recording.Hold it steady, hold it steady.
拍到了
I got it.
她通过了，她到达了浅水
She's gone past, Mike,she's in the pool.
好！ 我要过去了
OK, get in there.
她抓到一个，别错过了
She's got one, definitely,you can't mistake it.
带走它，带远一点，快！
Bringing it out now.Taking it straight out.
拖它离开
She's pulling it out.
拖下海里面
Out to sea...
她把它拖下去了
Taking it under.
上帝, 它被拖走了
God, he just got hammered.
我觉得非常兴奋，不过又有点悲伤…真的
Part of me's elated that I've got it,but part of me's sad, really,
因为我看着，这些小海狮
cos I've watched these little characters,
这些天，看着她们成长
these pups grow in the last few weeks
然而虎鲸也一样，他们只是进行了一次成功的狩猎
and the orcas too,they've got to survive and they've made a successful hunt
他们现在去继续他们的旅程了，我们能说些什么呢？
and they're now continuing their journey, so what can you say?
亲眼目睹这类事情，我们常常会感概万千
Witnessing such events often results in such a conflict of emotions.
二个星期的拍摄完成了，虎鲸也离开了
The two-week window is over and the killer whales move on.
要一年后，她们才会再来这里
It'll be a whole year before this exceptional female
再开杀戒
returns here to hunt again.